Inside this lecture.
Let me try to provide a formal definition of microservice so that if someone asks you, you should be
able to answer it quickly and easily.
You don't have to explain all the concepts that we discussed previously to a non-technical person.
So if some business user or if some client asks you what is the definition of microservice or what are
microservice, then you can tell this definition.
And this definition is defined by the James Lewis and Martin Fowler's in one of the blog article that
they have written.
So like you can see, microservices is an approach to develop a single application as a suit of small
services inside easy bank web application, we can develop a web application as a suit of small services
with the name accounts, loans and cards.
And each of these services, they can run in their own process and they can communicate with lightweight
mechanisms like rest and all these microservices built around business capabilities or business domains.
And most importantly, they can independently deployable by fully automated deployment machinery.
We can automate everything like as soon as a developer check in into the code base of a microservice,
the build will happen and the same build will be deployed automatically into dev and uat environment.
And if needed, we can also automate the deployment into production using CI/CD concept.
So there are many, many advantages with microservice which we are going to learn inside this course.
But on a high level this is going to be your simple go to definition of microservice.
I hope this is helpful to you, especially when you're talking with non-technical persons.
Then please use this definition.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.